a few weeks ago I published an article
on my blog that really stimulated a lot
of debate that article is called the
real reason conservatives always win and
in it I took the argument put forth in
this book the social conquest of Earth
by Edward Wilson it took his basic
argument which is that groups that have
greater cohesion tend to win over groups
that have less cohesion and I applied
that argument to us politics making the
claim that conservatives in the United
States have much deeper or social
cohesion and have invested in
infrastructure that allows them to work
in a coordinated fashion where as
progressives tend to be divided into
issue silos and don't have the
investments in infrastructure especially
media and organizing skills capabilities
and so progressives tend to lose and I
want to explore that a little bit
further today as we look to the future
and think about the upcoming
presidential election in the United
States as well as more broadly the
challenges that we face in addressing
global problems such as climate change
and resource depletion where this
question of group cohesion is really
fundamental and asking ourselves will
humanity be able to come together on a
global scale and deal with our problems
and so the basic argument that Wilson
laid out in this book is that the social
organization of animals that have social
behavior such as ants and termites bees
and of course humans enables those
species that are able to form stronger
social organization to be able to
out-compete those individual species
that cannot form such strong group
cohesion and there's plenty of evidence
for why this might be the case but in
the context of us politics and I think
more broadly in the global approach to
dealing with things like climate we have
to ask this question of what does it
take to create group cohesion how does
group cohesion work
and how can we learn from what we're now
getting a sense of from science about
group cohesion to be able to tackle
these problems and Wilson does a nice
job of laying out why it's so important
for us to be asking this question but he
doesn't give the complete answer on his
own and so I picked up another book this
one here moral origins the evolution of
virtue altruism and shame by the
anthropologist Christopher bone and
started reading it because Bowman asks a
very fundamental question he asks how is
it that social morality arises in the
particular kinds of groups that are in
human ancestry specifically the long
period of time where we lived in
hunter-gatherer societies and his
argument is that the fundamental
selection pressure for groups over
individuals arose in the context of
hunting for big game and the need for
small groups of people in their tribes
to be able to punish bullies or
dictators people who would cheat in game
the the hunting system to be able to get
advantage for themselves to the
detriment of the group and so his
suggestion was that the the rise of the
social behavior of altruism can be
linked with the punishment or the
punitive aspects of shame and that those
who would try to take more for
themselves would be shamed by their
group and of course everyone in the
group knew each other so the shaming
could be very effective and an ultimate
form of shaming would be to ostracize or
kick that cheater out of the group which
would lead to almost certain death in
those times because survival outside of
the group was so precarious so as we
think about last year with the rise of
the Occupy movement and we asked
ourselves how is it that global
civilization is dealing with the
cheaters or those who game the global
economy for individual gained over the
collective well-being that same
fundamental question that
hunter-gatherer societies have been
grabbed
with all the way back to antiquity and
the rise of social organization and our
species that's been a fundamental thread
and so Christopher bomb has been trying
to answer that question one of the
things that he suggests is that the way
that we understand how social behavior
is reinforced is to first look at how
antisocial behavior is punished and now
that's not the end of the story but it's
a very important beginning piece and I
think we should hold on to that as we
ask this question of how do we develop
frameworks for cooperation especially at
a scale larger than individual cultures
such as the global scale to do with big
problems and that questions like what
Christopher bounzer as grap as grappling
with are going to be very very important
now we actually have some research
historic research in modern times take
this out of that hunter-gatherer
contacts and helps us begin to answer
this question of how does cooperation
work in the complexities of modern
society and this book here my Robert
Paxton the anatomy of fascism is
actually a really helpful helpful kind
of a teachable moment for thinking about
how cooperation can lead us astray is
what Paxton asked himself was he
basically asked how is it that a group
of people can use a democratic process
to establish a dictatorship which is
somewhat the opposite of what Krista
Boehm was saying about hunter-gatherer
societies where the egalitarian ethos
and the social morality of sharing
that's so essential for tribal
communities to survive could actually be
subverted through a tribal identity that
enables a group of elites to evoke that
tribal identity and then place a
dictator at the helm of the civilization
which is what happened with mussolini
and italy post-world War one it's what
happened in the Third Reich in Germany
first world war one and entering into
World War two and we can see threads of
it today
envia the Elimination 'used and hate
based rhetoric of the Tea Party of the
john birch society here in the united
states were these groups that have very
strong tribal identity and of course
this is more broadly an issue with with
fundamentalist groups fundamentalist
religious groups around the world so
this question of how do we do a
terrorism how do we keep strong social
cohesion of those groups that seek to
dominate other groups through and
through authoritarian mindset how do we
handle them well one of the ways we
begin to answer that is to look at what
we know about fascism and of course
fascism is an unusual mix of shared
social identity a strong belief in an
inherent superiority of one group over
another and the cohesion of that group
to be able to rise and dominate Lofton
ironically threw the democratic process
to get a majority of people to vote for
an elite group to dominate society and
so there are some perversities there
that we need to grapple with but really
the question that I see the way needy
answer is how do we take these kinds of
questions you know the nature of group
cohesion how it allows one group to help
compete another and how sometimes group
cohesion can enable bullies to dominate
and set up dictatorships when we ask the
questions how does all that work one of
the fundamental questions that comes to
mind is how does a group of people evoke
a cultural meme which means a way of
thinking about the world that becomes
provocative and it spreads across
different communities of people to
enable either cooperation that is
beneficial to the group or cooperation
that leads to subjugation of the group
and what we found historically is it the
only way that human beings could form
greater strength than individuals was to
form organizations and until recently
the only way that we could form
organizations was through a kind of
centralized top-down command and control
you could almost think of it as the
industrial model
of manufacturing applied to division of
labor so you would have an executive who
would lead an organization that would
then sudden agenda and would create a
kind of subjugation for the workers and
this is what we call um you know today
we think about people who work a job to
get a wage because they can't survive
and provide for their own without having
a job that pays for their salary that's
a kind of on coercion where they are
coerced by a need for money to work
within a system that subjugates them to
that system and then there's a
centralized management structure that
enables the owner of that organization
which may be the investors in the
corporation and that they are then able
to have undue influence and power over
the workers and create a system with
strong social cohesion that actually
creates a kind of centralized control
now recently there have been a number of
breakthroughs in the way that we
organize society in the way that we
organize people to get things done then
has broken out of this mold and it's
been driven by the digital
communications and software computing
technology revolutions of the last 40 to
50 years and so we see that if we look
at phenomena like the open-source
software movement and this book here the
success of open-source by Steven Weber
lays out in very clear detail how it is
that the economics and the politics of
group collaboration can happen without
there being any centralized command and
control system and so the basic question
is how can a group of people with a
shared affinity and a shared agenda
organize themselves without a
centralized Authority and that has now
been demonstrated through projects like
the formation of the Linux operating
system the creation of Wikipedia as an
open-source platform for building and
sharing knowledge and those basic
questions are being answered one of the
critical ones is what is the cost of the
economic transaction for like minded
people to find each other and distribute
their labor
and with online tools email discussion
forums blogs Twitter and Facebook
qualities social media and group
organizing tools enable people to
aggregate themselves at a very low cost
of time and effort to be able to work on
very large projects without their
needing to be a centralized control
which means for the first time ever we
can replace a kind of fascist top-down
centralized management system with a
much more open collaborative transparent
distributed leadership system there's
been plenty of writing about how this
works I'll give two examples one is from
Clay Shirky he's written several books
but this one really lays out the core
ideas here comes everybody and the
subtitle is revolution doesn't happen
when society adopts new technology it
happens when society adopts new
behaviors and so this book is about the
poor power of organizing without
organizations and Clay Shirky explains
include clear detail that supports
Steven Weber's work that we now have the
technology and the cultural knowledge of
practices and leadership models for
governance and decision-making that
enable us to organize ourselves without
centralized authorities now another set
of work that helps support this is this
crowdsourcing why the power of the crowd
is driving the future of business by
Jeff how you probably heard of
crowdsourcing crowdsourcing is the set
of techniques and technologies and
cultural norms and practices that enable
groups of people to organize themselves
into collectives to get things done and
so it's a way of creating innovation
through collective action which means
we're actually tackling this problem of
how does cooperation work without
dictatorships in a practical way by
building tools and creating communities
of practice that actually do it and
they're demonstrating it through the
success of their efforts and this is
leading to a lot of interesting things
such as as this book describes the rise
of collaborative consumption
collaborative consumption being a new
model
of group effort that is based on a
different way of thinking about property
and ownership so one of the big
challenges for breaking out of the model
of capitalism we've had in the last
three centuries is that the typical way
of thinking about economic productivity
is that those who can control and
exclude others from using resources
whether that's land whether it's access
to minerals whether it's access to ideas
and information that those people are
able to then invest effort and through
paying money for creating organizations
and hiring people to do work to create
value and then monetary return off of
the ownership of those commodities and
what we're finding is that we can now
flip that on its head and distribute
ownership and create shared value across
the community of people who find common
value in the access to that thing and
that thing might be shared access to
cars like the way the zipcar or car
sharing programs work where you don't
have to exclude others from having the
car to be able to get value from it and
the shared access is what creates value
it could be land management practices
like what the Land Conservancy does
where access to productive land is
something that creates value for
everyone especially when we're talking
about the land creating value like
floodplains that protect from damage to
cities or farm land or water management
where the need to have a sustainable
management practice so we don't run out
of water is to the benefit of everyone
and so a collaborative model of
ownership enables everyone to put a
stake in and for people to monitor each
other to be sure the resource isn't
exploited in a way that hurts the
long-term viability of the community and
there have been some models of how this
works that actually go much more into a
sophisticated discussion of how
economies work and i'll just give two
examples one is this one regional
advantage by amelie sex and sex na n and
this book explores the difference in the
innovation ecosystem between the the
corridor of businesses around boston vs
the corridor of business
as in Silicon Valley in the Bay Area in
California and what is really
interesting about the research that
Emily does or what she did in this is
she explored how the culture of
collaboration of open sharing of ideas
of people moving from one company to
another where they share an affinity for
innovation rather than a loyalty to a
specific tribe which would be their
company and having a larger affinity to
the tribe of the innovation scene in
Silicon Valley how that enabled the
group to innovate more quickly to
distribute ideas to build on each
other's success and to create really
robust regional economies that are able
to out-compete other economies which is
why the term regional advantage is
described here that Silicon Valley has
been able to out-compete other
technology spaces by having this
collaborative framework of open sharing
while also having built into it a set of
practices around business and innovation
and profit sharing as well as investing
to make money so it's kind of a hybrid
of different models now of course all of
that works because there's a deeper
collaboration happening just that in the
united states throughout the last 70
years we have pooled or taxpayer money
to invest in a publication education
system to create national research
laboratories to build on research
universities we have this vast
infrastructure of basic science and
basic education that has enabled this
layer of competition to happen on top of
the fundamental infrastructure of
collaboration and a great book that
explores how that works is this one
closing the innovation gap with Judy
Astrid what Judy does is she lays out
how that innovation infrastructure
funded through a deep level of
collaboration at the community level has
enabled the competitive activities of
our economy to be innovation drivers
because they built on a foundation of
deep investments in long-term
collaboration so competition and
collaboration are not that odds with
each other but they actually work in a
fortuitous loop at different levels and
so if we fail to invest in shared
infrastructure then we lose the ability
to compete
with each other internally at the
industrial level but also externally to
compete with other economies and so it's
not whether we compete or collaborate
but how we do both in a model that's
hybrid builds on the strengths of each
one and ultimately this whole set of
ideas about how does collaboration work
what's the nature of competition what is
our underlying evolutionary biology tell
us about how groups how human groups
have done this throughout antiquity it
all builds up to I think a very
important question which is how does the
change in human culture impact our
ability to activate or competitive or or
cooperative drives because they're both
part of human nature and that leads to a
really provocative question that
question being that how does human
civilization move from being profoundly
selfish short-term and it's thinking
competitive and exploitative which is
destroying the global environment and
calling into question the viability of
human civilization how do we get from
that mode of human behavior to a
different one where we have global scale
collaboration to protect the
infrastructure and the ecosystems that
we depend upon for our survival so that
instead of being a destructive force on
the planet that we become a restorative
force or something akin to being
stewards of the economic productivity if
you will of the global economy and
actually have three books here that make
the case that that is both possible and
in some ways that we're actively moving
toward it and one of them is this book
here here on earth a natural history of
the planet x 10 Flannery Tim Flannery
has studied the history of planetary
evolution so how did the planet form how
did plate tectonics change the landforms
how did different kinds of plants and
animals evolve on those landforms and he
takes that deep historic geologic
effective and then he asks questions
about how it is that humanity arose in
the particular historical climatic and
geologic contexts that we arose in and
how is it that the the global patterns
the planetary patterns of living systems
creating a range of a temperature of
ocean acidity of amounts of carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere all these key
measures that are within a very delicate
range that allows life to survive on the
planet how actually living systems have
enabled that one example being that the
amount of carbon dioxide in the
atmosphere today is much much lower than
it was for the first billion years of
the planets history and also the amount
of oxygen is much much higher and we
know that the only thing that could
create that influx of oxygen and that
reduction of carbon in the atmosphere is
life itself in particular photosynthesis
photosynthesis being the process that
pulls carbon out of the atmosphere in
the form of carbon dioxide stores it in
the body of carbon-based beings and then
in the process consuming oxygen but also
releasing carbon monoxide which is then
better able to elevate the amount of
oxygen and reduce the amount of carbon
dioxide so throughout history living
systems have enabled the planet to
maintain up and operating range that's
conducive to life for those you who r
studt observers you'll know that this is
called the Gaia theory and it was
introduced by James Lovelock the idea
that living systems themselves have
enabled the planet to evolve dynamically
to a place that's conducive to life if
we take that idea very seriously and ask
how can humanity become something more
like the life-support system or the
immune system of the planet then we're
really talking about how does human
culture evolved in a way that we have a
profound cooperation with the planets
ecosystems and there are two other books
that I want to share that make the case
that we're actually going through that
cultural evolution process now
one of them is this one right here the
cultural creatives by Paul ray and the
cultural creatives is a large
sociological study so it's surveys focus
group studies interviews questionnaires
what that have asked more than a hundred
thousand people about their values and
their preferences over the last few
decades and what Paul ray is shown in
this work is that there's actually a
trend toward more ecological thinking
deeper relationship with the environment
I moved from materialistic and
hedonistic values more toward community
values and quality of life values and
that we can actually see that markedly
as an intergenerational pattern so we
are moving toward the kinds of cultural
expression that would enable us as a
global civilization to make this
transition to being the life-support
system for the planet and I think even
more powerfully the argument is made in
this book the empathic civilization by
Jeremy Rifkin what Rifkin shows is that
there is a general trend that as any
society becomes more complex it has a
greater division of labor which means
there are more clarified roles for how
people can actively participate in that
society and that the ability to
understand those different roles is an
expression of an increase in empathy the
ability to see from different
perspectives see their value look across
them and see how they're part of
building the complexity of that society
and that as we look across time there's
a historic trend that as any
civilization becomes more complex it
also becomes more empathetic and that
the question of whether we become a
global sustainable civilization could
really be asked as can human cultural
evolution evolved the capacity for
embedding empathy in the infrastructure
of our society faster than our tendency
to be greedy selfish and short-term Anor
thinking which is going to lead to the
destruction of our civilization and so
that question is now before us and
luckily we have all of these resources
two years to help us answer that
question and what I would like to
suggest based on the research I've been
doing and reading these books and
talking to researchers who study these
things is that I want to suggest that we
now have a scientifically rigorous set
of knowledge and methodologies that come
from different fields anthropology
neuroscience psychology linguistics
history evolutionary biology and in even
more and in these different fields were
actually seeing a converging picture of
human nature that reveals our true
complexity that shows us that this
choice of which part of human nature to
elevate is something that is a real and
empirically valid and we can actually
look at our success or failure where
have we created fascism where have three
writers bullies and cheaters been able
to game systems for their benefit what
kind of governing systems enable us to
regulate against those societal harms
the answer that we're finding is that
there's a mix of socialism in the sense
of investing in infrastructure for
societal well-being that means public
education that means universal health
care that means investing in science and
medicine and hospitals and public health
investing in the infrastructure for
business through courts and through on
trade associations through stock markets
etc etc all this societal infrastructure
and at the same time building governing
systems that are democratic which means
they elevate the power of individuals to
make empowered choices and asik
fulfillment but the democracy has to be
a modern democracy meaning that it has
to be pluralistic because societies are
obviously pluralistic when you look at
the different kinds of cultures that are
out there and so we need to have
parliamentary multi-party systems that
enable each group in society to be able
to have a clarified articulated voice
for its tribe while also being able to
defer its conflicts to a higher level
that has neutrality and that can
actually promote
justice in society which means that
those groups can form their own parties
in their governing system and that they
can have proportional representation and
that they can actually form coalition's
with like-minded people and other tribes
meaning other political parties in order
to maintain the stability of their
society while also having negotiations
compromise and disagreement that doesn't
devolve into polarization and division
course in the United States we can see
that we have a two-party system that
proposal that that promotes in a dynamic
way promotes that you're either part of
one camp or another or you have no voice
which makes it over time it polarizes
and divides us and anyone who doesn't
agree with those two perspectives is
basically left out just one of the
reasons why so few people vote in the
United States we have you know forty
percent of the voting public is who
shows up to elections the other sixty
percent don't feel like the system the
governing system we have represents
their voice and we can also see that
this two-party system has enabled a
corporate elite to establish a kind of
economic dictatorship and the conflict
between all of those groups who aren't
able to find real and meaningful
negotiation while at the same time
keeping in check the bullies we end up
with things like Occupy Wall Street
which is an expression of frustration by
a society of people in the US and
actually globally because this is the
case in many countries where we do not
have governing and economic systems that
promote social welfare investments in
societal infrastructure and empowered
pluralistic democracy so anywhere we
don't have that we need to create it
that's true at the local community level
at the National societal level and also
at the global level to the way that we
form trade agreements international
courts and ultimately ways of managing
the global Commons on a scale that's
larger than nations so at all those
levels we have to build on these
insights about human nature if we're
going to succeed so I hope that this is
helpful and useful to you
because I've been studying these things
to enable me to be able to grapple these
questions and help groups that are
trying to build robust pathways to
global sustainability and social justice
but I also help it's that it's useful to
you in your work so um if you have any
questions please feel free to just write
to me I blog at cognitive policy works
com as well as my personal blog chaotic
ripple calm and and I'm constantly
researching these things and talking
with people about them finding
like-minded people who are studying them
and trying to aggregate the insights
that they bring together so maybe you
have some insights some pieces of the
puzzle that I don't have or maybe you
want to learn more about what's already
here either way I hope this is useful to
you and I wish you the best of luck in
doing your part to be empowered to
create positive social change to lead us
toward a global configuration of
cooperation and sustainability thank you